Clinton C. Hurlbut Papers
© 2003 University of Connecticut
Clinton C. Hurlbut Papers.
undated, 1868-1975.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
Hurlbut, Clinton C., 1895-1974.
2 linear feet.
The collection consists of a switchyard layout diagram, published materials, photographs, and a signalman's hand lamp belonging to New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad signal superintendent Clinton C. Hurlbut, who worked for the railroad from 1912 to 1961.
MSS20030059
Biography
Clinton C. Hurlbut was born in 1895 in Essex, Connecticut. At a young age his family moved to Clinton, Connecticut, where he attended Morgan Academy. He started working for the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad in 1912 as a lineman and at some point moved to the Signal Department. He was a signal superintendent at age 23. Prior to 1934 he was stationed in Brooklyn, New York, and Waterbury, Connecticut. After 1934 and to his retirement he worked in Hartford, Connecticut. His duties included installing switchyard signals, electric signals, high tension signals, and controls in railroad signal towers. In 1953, due to heart problems, he stepped down from his position as a signal superintendent and worked as a signal maintainer until his retirement in 1961. After retirement he moved back to Clinton, Connecticut.
Clinton C. Hurlbut died on March 25, 1974.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of a switchyard layout diagram, published materials, photographs, and a signalman's hand lamp belonging to New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad signal superintendent Clinton C. Hurlbut, who worked for the railroad from 1912 to 1961.
Arrangement
Series I: Papers, 1868-1930s, consists of a large diagram of the Hartford, Connecticut, switchyard for the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad. Other papers include four issues (1868-1872) of Journal of the Telegraph, a list of pay rates for railroad jobs, and a copy of G.R.S. Model 2A Signal from 1918.
Series II: Photographs, 1889-1975, consists of 46 images of signal crews, signal equipment, railroad cars and cabooses, steam engines, and flooding on railroad tracks during the 1936 Hartford area floods. Locations in Connecticut include East Waterville, Killingworth, Middletown, New Britain, Old Saybrook, Plainville, Terryville, and Waterbury. Also includes photographs of Niagara Falls in New York and Kent Falls in Connecticut.
Series III: Memorabilia, ca. 1920s, consists of the signalman's hand lamp. Initials "C.C.H." etched in the back.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of New England railroad materials. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Hurlbut, CLinton C.
Organizations:
Family Names:
Places:
Subjects:
Document Types:
Publications.; Photographs.; Blueprints.
Occupations:
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Papers, 1868-1930s
  - N.Y.N.H.& H.R.R. Classification Yard. Hartford, Conn. [Hand-drawn diagram of switchyard layout], 1930s (Box 1)
  - G.R. S. Model 2A Signal, Booklet 1003A, 1918 December (Box 2:1)
  - Rates of Jobs in Classification, 1945 (Box 2:2)
  - Journal of the Telegraph, Vol. I, no. 23, 1868 October 15 (Box 2:3)
  - Journal of the Telegraph, Vol. II, no. 22 (whole no. 47), 1869 October 15 (Box 2:4)
  - Journal of the Telegraph, Vol. III, no. 1 (whole no. 50), 1869 December 1 (Box 2:5)
  - Journal of the Telegraph, Vol. V, no. 8 (whole no. 105), 1872 March 15 (Box 2:6)
- Series II: Photographs,undated, 1889-1975
  [Note: Photographs ph1 - ph24 are adhered to the back of the switchyard layout.]
  - 2003-0059.ph1 (Box 1)
    - Plainville, 1912. Switchbox open to reveal electrical workings, 1912
  - 2003-0059.ph2 (Box 1)
    - Looking East from ___ ___, 1913. View of unknown tracks from high vantage point, 1913
  - 2003-0059.ph3 (Box 1)
    - [Tracks and electrical poles]. Photograph damaged, half of image available,undated
  - 2003-0059.ph4 (Box 1)
    - 46 East End Terryville Tunnel. Steam locomotive emerging from tunnel, possible station on right, undated
  - 2003-0059.ph5 (Box 1)
    - [Niagara Falls] from __?__ Island, 1914. Partial and damaged, 1914
  - 2003-0059.ph6 (Box 1)
    - Wooster St. New Britain, 1912. Railroad crossing sign, two unidentified men posed behind, sitting on fence, 1912
  - 2003-0059.ph7 (Box 1)
    - W. S___, C.C. Hurlbut, C.R. Grove, Work Car, 306 New Britain, 1912.Three men posing in front of railroad work car,1912
  - 2003-0059.ph8 (Box 1)
    - A. Schwartz, East Waterville, 1913. Man standing at top of tall signal tower, 1913
  - 2003-0059.ph9 (Box 1)
    - Terryville, 1913. Posed shot of C.C. Hurlbut, 1913
  - 2003-0059.ph10 (Box 1)
    - Bristol, 1921. Nine men, probably a signal crew, posed in front of building, train visible in background. Photograph torn,1921
  - 2003-0059.ph11 (Box 1)
    - East Main St., New Britain, 1922. Motor Car No. 226 + no. 863.Ten men, probably a signal crew, posed on two railroad work cars,1922
  - 2003-0059.ph12 (Box 1)
    - Niagara from Suspension Bridge, 191[?], 1910s
  - 2003-0059.ph13 (Box 1)
    - _?_ Main St., New Britain, 1922. Eleven men, probably a signal crew, posed on railroad tracks. Hurlbut standing in back. One man is doing a handstand on the rail, 1922
  - 2003-0059.ph14 (Box 1)
    - Kent Falls, 1921. Colorized photograph of waterfall, 1921
  - 2003-0059.ph15 (Box 1)
    - Kent Falls, 1921. Colorized photograph of waterfall, 1921
  - 2003-0059.ph16 (Box 1)
    - Derby Jct., 1929. Nine men, probably a signal crew, posed on platform of caboose 503307, 1929
  - 2003-0059.ph17 (Box 1)
    - C.A. Warren, W. Fulton[?], 1935. Three men sitting on sideboard of a truck. Truck has "NYNH&HRR" sign on side, 1935
  - 2003-0059.ph18 (Box 1)
    - Middletown, 1935. Five men posed in front of railroad building. Tracks at left, 1935
  - 2003-0059.ph19 (Box 1)
    - Windham St., 1936. Four men standing on tracks which are partially submerged in floodwaters. Location unknown but known to be the Hartford area during the floods of March 1936,1936
  - 2003-0059.ph20 (Box 1)
    - Clif. Rose, C.C. Hurlbut. Windham St., 1936.Two men, somewhat shadowed, standing on railroad ties, work train in background, amid floodwaters on tracks,1936
  - 2003-0059.ph21 (Box 1)
    - Derby Jct. 1929. Six men standing in front of railroad caboose with sign on side "M of W Signal 505307 Waterbury _?_." These men are also in photograph 2003-0059.ph16, 1929
  - 2003-0059.ph22 (Box 1)
    - Derby Loop, 1919, Eng. 3213. Right side view of New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad steam locomotive, 1919
  - 2003-0059.ph23 (Box 2:7)
    - _?_ _?_ _?_ switch, 19??. Crossing signal, tracks in background. Snow on ground,1900s
  - 2003-0059.ph24 (Box 2:7)
    - Derby Jct., 1913. Ray Coulan, Allen Schwartz, John Doyle, Barney McFeeley, Bill Fitzgerald, Frank Walker. Six men sitting or standing next to railroad work car, 1913
  - 2003-0059.ph25 (Box 2:7)
    - [Unidentified steam engine, ca. late 1930s or early 1940s.] Probably engine 1400, 1930s-1940s
  - 2003-0059.ph26 (Box 2:7)
    - [Unidentified steam engine, ca. 1930s] ,1930s
  - 2003-0059.ph27 (Box 2:7)
    - Bank St. Waterbury, S.S. 202. Empty railroad tracks, station on right, undated
  - 2003-0059.ph28 (Box 2:7)
    - Bridge at Ninevah Killingworth, Conn. Stream with automobile traffic bridge overhead, undated
  - 2003-0059.ph29 (Box 2:7)
    - [Man standing on top of electrical tower.] Probably "Augie" Schwartz, 1913?
  - 2003-0059.ph30 (Box 2:7)
    - [Augie Schwartz standing on top of signal tower], 1913?
  - 2003-0059.ph31 (Box 2:7)
    - [Augie Schwartz], 1913?
  - 2003-0059.ph32 (Box 2:7)
    - S.S. 214, 1889. Brick building, Hartford signal tower, 1889
  - 2003-0059.ph33 (Box 2:7)
    - Wooster St. New Britain, 1921. Five men standing on railroad tracks, 1921
  - 2003-0059.ph34 (Box 2:7)
    - Stanley St., New Britain, 1922. Eleven men, probably a signal crew, standing or kneeling on railroad tracks, 1922
  - 2003-0059.ph35 (Box 2:7)
    - East Main St., New Britain, 1922. Ten men, probably a signal crew, standing or sitting on railroad tracks, 1922
  - 2003-0059.ph36 (Box 2:7)
    - [Two men sitting on work car, 1922?], 1922?
  - 2003-0059.ph37 (Box 2:7)
    - New Britain, 1922. Eight men, probably a signal crew, sitting on or standing next to a work car, 1922
  - 2003-0059.ph38 (Box 2:7)
    - [Augie Schwartz sitting on work car], 1922
  - 2003-0059.ph39 (Box 2:7)
    - C. Warren Vacation, East H____ ___, 1931. Man asleep in a hammock on a covered porch, 1931
  - 2003-0059.ph40 (Box 2:7)
    - Pop. - Paul. - Clint. - Chas. - Al. - Bill. 1934 Six men standing on railroad tracks. Includes "Pop" Barnes and Clinton Hurlbut, 1934
  - 2003-0059.ph41 (Box 2:7)
    - [Three men standing at the side of a truck with NYNH&HRR on its side], 1935
  - 2003-0059.ph42 (Box 2:7)
    - S.S. __ 274, 1937. Signal tower with industrial building and water tower on each side, 1937
  - 2003-0059.ph43 (Box 2:7)
    - Hap Warner. Information on back reads "'The Man of the Hour,' Mr. Irving Warner, 3-25-38, America's Last Bearded Signalman", 1938
  - 2003-0059.ph44 (Box 2:7)
    - 1400 Eng. At Guilford, 1941. Blurred image of steam engine billowing steam, 1941
  - 2003-0059.ph45 (Box 2:7)
    - Old Saybrook Tower 1973. Dilapidated signal tower, 1973
  - 2003-0059.ph46 (Box 2:7)
    - [Old Saybrook Signal Tower]. Reads on back: "Old Saybrook Signal Tower built in 1912 to replace former tower which was located across the tracks from present tower and was destroyed Oct., 8, 1912 when freight cars being switched rammed into it and tower operator William Wilcox was killed in the accident", 1975
- Series III: Memorabilia, 1920s
  - Railroad signalman's handlamp. Initials "C.C.H." etched in back,ca. 1920s (Box 3)